If we think about the aetiology of anxiety disorders from a cognitive behavioral perspective,
Nếu ta nghĩ về nguyên nhân của rối loạn lo âu từ khía cạnh nhận thức-hành vi
the behavioral component is very much informed by Stanley Rachman’s work published in 1977.
thì yếu tố hành vi được giải thích khá kĩ bởi công trình của Stanley Rachman, xuất bản năm 1977
Rachman proposed three pathways through which people might develop fear.
Rachman đưa ra 3 lời giải về sự phát triển nỗi sợ trong con người
The first is through their own direct experience, which may become generalised through conditioning.
Đầu tiên là qua trải nghiệm của họ, thứ có thể được khái quát hóa qua sự điều kiện hóa
So, for example, if you have experienced a dog biting you in the face, you might acquire
Ví dụ, nếu bạn bị chó cắn vào mặt, bạn có thể sẽ sợ chó,
a fear of dogs, which might then generalise to various other animals – or not.
sau đó có thể là sợ các con vật khác nói chung - hoặc không
The second pathway is instructional learning, which involves the transmission of information
Cách thứ 2 là thông qua sự hướng dẫn, bao gồ việc truyền đạt thông tin về nguy hiểm
relating to danger.
relating to danger.
For example, when a parent repeatedly warns a child to stay away from pools because people
Ví dụ, khi bố mẹ liên tục nhắc nhở con mình tránh xa bể bơi
drown in pools all the time, the child might develop a fear of pools.
vì luôn có người bị chết đuối, đứa trẻ sẽ sinh ra sợ bể bơi
The third pathway that Rachman proposed was vicarious learning.
Các thứ 3 Rachman nêu ra là qua cách học gián tiếp
This is when you repeatedly see someone else, usually an important person in your life such
Khi bạn liên tục thấy một người khác, một người quan trọng với bạn
as a parent, behave fearfully when confronted by a particular stimulus, and then you develop
ví dụ như bố mẹ, trở nên sợ sệt khi phải đối mặt với một kích thích nhất định,
that fear yourself.
thì bạn cũng sẽ bắt đầu có nỗi sợ đó
So, that is a very behavioural perspective on the ways in which anxiety or fear may develop.
Đây là góc nhìn hành vi về cách mà sự lo âu và sợ hãi phát triển
Let’s have a look at the kind of cognitive-behavioural model that might be used to explain the way
Hãy quan sát mô hình nhận thức-hành vi dùng để giải thích sự hoạt động của nỗi lo với một người bệnh
anxiety works to a client.
anxiety works to a client.
I’ll talk you through an example – just the way I would with a client – to explain
Tôi sẽ giải thích qua một ví dụ- hệt như cách tối làm với bệnh nhân -
how the elements of this model fit together.
cách mà các yếu tố trên mô hình này liên kết với nhau
I’ll give you a bit of background information about Sam, the subject of our example.
Tôi sẽ cho bạn một ít thông tin bên lề về Sam, đối tượng ví dụ
Imagine that Sam is an only child, the son of quiet, introverted parents.
Tưởng tượng rằng Sam là con một, trong một gia đình ít nói, hướng nội
Growing up in a small country town, he was quite shy and didn’t have many friends.
Lớn lên ở một thị trấn nhỏ vùng quê, câu bé khá ngượng ngùng và không có nhiều bạn
His parents tended to keep to themselves and the family didn’t socialise very much.
Bố mẹ cậu thường giữ mình và không giao du nhiều
Now Sam is at university and living in college.
Bây giờ Sam đang học đại học và sống ở đó
One of the guys on his floor, Pete, asks him if he wants to go to a party.
Một người sống cùng tầng tên Pete mời cậu đi tham gia một bữa tiệc
Sam says yes.
Sam đồng ý
He arrives at the party by himself.
Cậu ta tự đến bữa tiệc một mình
He gets as far as the open doorway to the house, where he can see people laughing, talking
Cậu ta thậm chí đã mở cửa và thấy mọi người cười nói vui vẻ
and having a good time.
and having a good time.
But he can’t see the mate who invited him.
Nhưng lại không thấy được cậu bạn đã mời mình tham gia
No-one comes to greet Sam.
Không ai đến chào mừng Sam
He thinks to himself, “This is going to be awful.
Cậu nghĩ: "Việc này thật tệ
I can’t see Pete…actually I can’t see anyone I know.
Mình không thấy Pete... thực ra mình không thấy ai mình quen biết
No-one is going to talk to me and I am going to look like a real loser.
Không ai sẽ đến nói chuyện với mình và mình sẽ trông thảm hại
I wish I had never come”.
Ước gì mình chưa từng tới đây"
This is an example of the cognitive system in action.
Đây là một ví dụ về sự hoạt động của hệ thần kinh
As he is saying this to himself, Sam notices that his heart is beating really fast, that
Khi đang tự nhủ với bản thân, Sam nhận ra tim mình đập rất nhanh
his hands have gone all sweaty, and that he has become flushed in the face. All manifestations
bàn tay đầy mồ hôi và mặt đỏ bừng.
of the physiological system of anxiety.
Tất cả dấu hiệu của hệ thống sinh lý khi lo âu
And here we have a nasty little feedback loop between the physiological and the cognitive
Rồi sau đó ta có một phản hồi tồi tệ móc nối giữa hệ thống sinh lý và nhận thức
system, because, having noticed his physical symptoms of anxiety, Sam says to himself,
bời vì, sau khi nhận ra các dấu hiệu cơ thể của sự lo âu, Sam nói với bản thân
“Great.
"Tuyệt. Giờ mọi người sẽ thấy mình lo lắng thế nào"
Now, everyone is going to be able to see what a nervous wreck I am”.
Now, everyone is going to be able to see what a nervous wreck I am”.
His feelings of anxiety and uneasiness increase, and eventually, he turns around and leaves
Cảm xúc của cậu ta đối với sự lo âu và không thoải mái gia tăng và cuối cùng
the party.
khiến cậu ta quay đầu rời khỏi bữa tiệc
When he leaves (which is the behavioural system of anxiety in action), he is avoiding the
Khi cậu ta rời đi (dưới tác dụng của hệ thống hành vi khi lo âu) tức là cậu ta
stimulus (the party) and the thoughts that have made him anxious.
đang trốn tránh kích thích (bữa tiệc) và các suy nghĩ gây lo lắng
The immediate consequence of his avoidance is that Sam’s anxiety reduces.
Kết quả tức thời của việc chạy trốn là mức độ lo âu của Sam giảm đi
As he is walking away however, Sam thinks to himself, “Well, I was right.
Trên đường về nhà, tuy nhiên, Sam nghĩ: "Mình đã làm đúng.
I couldn’t cope in that situation and it was every bit as awful as I knew it was going
Mình không quen với tình hình lúc đó và nó đúng là tệ như mình đã nghĩ"
to be”.
to be”.
His avoidance has served to reinforce or strengthen his original negative thoughts…and next
Sự trốn tránh của cậu ta đã khẳng định lại những suy nghĩ tiêu cực ban đầu
time he is invited to a party, Sam is much less likely to accept the invitation.
và lần sau khi được mời đi dự tiệc, Sam sẽ khó mà nhận lời
Whether Sam is a 20 year old university student (as in this example), a 65 year old, a 13
Cho dù Sam là một sinh viên đại học 20 tuổi (theo như ví dụ), một người 65, 13 hay 5 tuổi cũng thế
year old, or a 5 year old is irrelevant.
year old, or a 5 year old is irrelevant.
Anxiety works in the same way for adults, adolescents and children.
Sự lo âu vận hành y hệt đối với người lớn, người vị thành niên và trẻ nhỏ